Faiz Ahmed Farooqui

www.faizahmed.in . faizz.af@gmail.com . Bengaluru, India

Experienced & result-driven IT Infrastructure Software Engineer, with strong experience in providing strategy, planning and implementation for various projects and companies. A sophisticated understanding of the analysis, design, and implementation of every aspect of the concerned project, be it the backend, frontend, mobile devices, testing and devops.

Skills

Programming: Javascript, PHP, HTML

Backend: Laravel, NodeJS, ExpressJS,

WordPress

Frontend: jQuery, ReactJS, VueJS,

AngularJS, React Native

Environments: MacOS, CentOS, Ubuntu

Storage: MySQL, MariaDB, MongoDB,

Redis, AWS Aurora

Tools: Git, Postman, JIRA, Trello,

Webpack

DevOps: Docker, AWS Code Deploy, AWS CodePipeline, Circle Cl, BitBucketCl, GitLabCl AWS EC2, DigitalOcean Droplets & Hetzner

Open Source Contributions

HackerNews ● https://github.com/faizahmedfarooqui/ycombinator-react

A HackerNews clone built using ReactJS, Firebase, Redux, KoaJS & Google Charts. It's an SSR web-app, hosted on the Heroku app. Note: The upvote functionality is locally implemented.

GA-WDIO • https://www.npmjs.com/package/ga-wdio • https://github.com/GeekyAnts/ga-wdio

An automation CLI tool that creates the tests project for Web, API & Mobile apps and runs tools like geckodriver, chromedriver & appium internally for various stacks, browsers, platforms & modes.

A boilerplate built in NodeJS without using NPM • https://github.com/faizahmedfarooqui/nodejs

A Web & API server with a CLI tool built using low-level NodeJS's APIs; i.e. without using any NPM packages.

A framework built in NodeJS using Typescript • https://github.com/geekyants/express-typescript

A framework built for Web & API servers using NodeJS, Typescript & various things that complete a frameworks requirement with Basic Authentication Logic already built.

Experience

GeekyAnts Software Private Limited, Bengaluru, India (Formerly known as Sahusoft India Private Limited)

September 2015 - Present

Provided full-stack development along with architectural solutions for Web App, Mobile App, CLI-tool & Backend. Worked with server-side process management, continuous integration/deployment solution and stakeholder management and resource management of the company.

Associate Director of Engineering

May 2021 - Present

Preacher and trainer of new things within the team • Reviewing code base logic of my team members • Following up with the agile flow to keep the team in sync with the features and timeline • Using git-flow to reduce as much of conflicts possible • Keep learning new things to help and make the team more efficient.

• Engineering Manager - Level 2

July 2019 - April 2021

Preacher and trainer of new things within the team • Reviewing code base logic of my team members • Following up with the agile flow to keep the team in sync with the features and timeline • Using git-flow to reduce as much of conflicts possible • Keep learning new things to help and make the team more efficient.

• Tech Lead August 2018 - June 2019

Preacher and trainer of new things within the team • Reviewing code base logic of my team members • Following up with the agile flow to keep the team in sync with the features and timeline • Using git-flow to reduce as much of conflicts possible • Keep learning new things to help and make the team more efficient.

• Senior Software Engineer

January 2018 - July 2018

Directing software development projects • Leading engineers & developers • Identify, prioritize and execute tasks in the software development lifecycle • Producing, testing & debugging code • Developing tools & applications by producing clean & efficient code • Knowledge of development tools for Version Control, Continuous Integration, Deployment & Delivery • In-depth knowledge of SQL & NoSQL databases • To have in-depth knowledge of the latest technologies in the backend as well as the frontend stack.

• Software Engineer

September 2015 - December 2017

Learning full-stack end-to-end web development • Understanding how queue/cron works in the background • Keep experimenting with new technologies on the web and mobile.

Education

Raj Kumar Goel Engineering College, Ghaziabad, India

March 2015

Completed Degree in Bachelor of Technology from Computer Science and Engineering branch with 74.56% aggregate from Uttar Pradesh Technical University.

Gulmohar Public School, Kanpur, Uttar Pradesh, India

March 2011

Completed Senior Secondary School (+2) with Science Stream with 75% aggregate from Central Board of Secondary Education.

Dr Omprakash Agarwal English High School, Bhiwandi, Maharashtra, India

March 2009

Completed Higher Secondary School from Maharashtra State Board.

Personal Information

LinkedIn: https://linkedin.com/in/faizahmedfarooqui GitHub: http://github.com/faizahmedfarooqui

Father's Name: Mr Raees Ahmed Farooqui Mother's Name: Mrs Aisha Farooqui

Nationality: Indian Languages: English & Hindi